<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Dr. E.S. concerning his late letter to Mr. G. and the account he gives in it of a conference between Mr. G. and himself from one who was present at the conference.</title>
            <author>Meredith, Edward, 1648-1689?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13148221</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13148221</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98084</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98084)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 428:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Dr. E.S. concerning his late letter to Mr. G. and the account he gives in it of a conference between Mr. G. and himself from one who was present at the conference.</title>
                  <author>Meredith, Edward, 1648-1689?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Discussion of a letter from Edward Stillingfleet to Thomas Godden.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: E.M.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Meredith. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"Publish'd with allowance"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Letter to Mr. G.</term>
               <term>Godden, Thomas, 1624-1688.</term>
               <term>Authority --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tradition (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98084:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER To Dr. E. S. CONCERNING His late Letter to Mr. <hi>G.</hi> and the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he gives in it of a <hi>Conference</hi> between Mr. <hi>G.</hi> and himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From one who was preſent at the Conference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd with Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, For his Houſhold and Chappel. 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98084:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98084:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER To Dr. <hi>E. S.</hi> Concerning his late Letter to Mr. <hi>G—</hi> and the Account he gives in it of a <hi>Conference</hi> between Mr. <hi>G—</hi> and himſelf.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MR. <hi>G—</hi>being now at a very great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from this Place, and it being great pity that his Reputation ſhould ſuffer ſo long (as it muſt needs be till you can receive an Anſwer to your Letter from himſelf), I think it will neither misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Chriſtian, nor a Friend, if (having been a Witneſs to the Conference you mention, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with Mr. <hi>G—</hi>both before and after it) I overcome the natural Repugnance I have of appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this manner, and offer ſome Things to your Conſideration, which (I ought to hope) will much conduce towards the reſtoring him, both to your good Opinion, and to that of the World, who being Strangers to the Matter of Fact, (I am confident) think worſe of it than you your ſelf do; tho' your Complaint ſeem to be ſo much in earneſt.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98084:3"/>
Wherefore I take the liberty of laying what I have to ſay, before you, as faithfully as a moſt ſincere deſire of ſpeaking nothing but Truth, and as fully as my Memory ſhall enable me.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, before the Conference Mr. <hi>G—</hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted me, that having affirm'd in ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, That no <hi>Proteſtants</hi> could ſhew any Ground of Abſolute Certainty for their Faith, one Mr. <hi>T—</hi> had promis'd him, That if you were not able to manifeſt the contrary, he would forſake your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; and that hereupon he had undertaken to Diſcourſe with you on this Subject. I mention this, that my Readers may know how the Conference was occaſion'd, and what was deſign'd for the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, that they may be the better Judges of what follow'd.</p>
            <p>The Hour of Conference being come, before any Arguments paſs'd, Mr. <hi>G—</hi>deſir'd, that what was ſaid on both Sides might be written down, for the prevention of ſuch Miſtakes as might otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and are very uſual in Things of this nature. This Proceeding was no Mark of one who wanted an Intention of dealing fairly, nor part of that <hi>great care, which,</hi> you ſay, <hi>he took to keep you from expecting any great Ingenuity from him;</hi> ſince nothing could ſavour of greater Candor, or more Ingenuity, than a Deſire of putting it out of his power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent that which paſs'd, any otherwiſe than in truth it was; which he manifeſtly ſhew'd by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, that it might be committed to Writing. Wherefore, if you had ſpar'd this Reflection, I am am apt to think, that you would have given a better Proof of that Ingenuity in your ſelf, which you ſeem to look on as wanting in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98084:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Mr. <hi>G—</hi> having deſir'd this, three Perſons ſate down to Write: The Gentleman whom you Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd was one, Mr. <hi>T—</hi> (the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> whom you Confirm'd) a Second, and Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Friend the Third.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Thing which was Propos'd, and indeed the only Subject, which (as I have already intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) Mr. <hi>G—</hi> had any purpoſe to Diſcourſe on, was <hi>Whether Proteſtants had a Ground of Abſolute Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for their Faith, or not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this Diſpute (which, I think, laſted about two Hours) tho' it was not carry'd on without ſome Wrangling, yet at length the Queſtions and Anſwers were Penn'd down with Quietneſs enough. They were alſo conſtantly Read aloud after they were Written, ſo that all the Writers had an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of rectifying what ſhould happen to be amiſs in their reſpective Copies. This Exactneſs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd during the Agitation of this Firſt and Chief Queſtion. But this Diſpute being broken off (after what manner, I ſhall tell you preſently) when the People grew weary, and (as it ſeldom fails on ſuch Occaſions) ſomewhat more Peeviſh, a new Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie was ſtarted, which laſted but a little while, and being manag'd with more Noiſe, and greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions (eſpecially towards the end) than the former, it might have been apprehended, that the Writers would not be able to obſerve the ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curateneſs which they had done before, and that thence might follow ſome little Diſagreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Copies. In a word, The Diſcourſe grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot, and Paſſion and Perſonal Reflections begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to take the place of Arguments, or, at leaſt, to mix with them, the Company roſe up, and Mr. <hi>T—</hi> being willing to preſerve the Peace, and conſidering
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98084:4"/>
(as I ſuppoſe) that it was late, declar'd that he was abundantly ſatisfi'd with your Reaſons, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſignifi'd his Deſire, that Mr. <hi>G—</hi> might not trouble you any farther; whereupon he was forc'd to put an end to his Argumentation, by Taking his leave. And here, I confeſs, there were ſome Things ſaid by both Sides, which were not written down; and it is not improbable, but that ſomewhat might be taken by one Writer, which was not by another. The Parting alſo was ſo abrupt and haſty, that no one thought of, or at leaſt, mention'd the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or Signing the Papers, but each Writer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any farther Ceremony, carry'd away his own Copy.</p>
            <p>Some Readers imagine by what you ſpeak of an <hi>Original Copy, read aloud, and approved by both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> that ſuch a Copy of the whole was Read at the end of the Conference, and ſo approved, which was not ſo; but the Queſtions and Anſwers were for the moſt part ſtill read as they were ſet down, in the manner I have here deſcribed.</p>
            <p>This is in General what I remember of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, of which I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more particularly hereafter.</p>
            <p>After the Conference Mr. <hi>G—</hi> deſired the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who wrote for him, to let him have the Copy he had taken: And proceeding <hi>bonâ fide,</hi> and knowing no Cauſe, why this Gentleman ſhould put a corrupt Copy into his hands, as alſo find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what he received to agree in Subſtance with what he himſelf remembred of the Diſpute, he had no reaſon to look on it any otherwiſe, than as ſufficiently exact, at leaſt, ſo much of it, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the firſt and principal Controverſie, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98084:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(as I have ſaid before) was more couriouſly taken notice of.</p>
            <p>Now, whereas you ſay, That Mr. <hi>G—made great boaſts of a Victory after the Conference,</hi> he was ſo far from it, that being then asked by ſome of his friends, what had been the iſſue of that rencounter, he anſwered that your Art was ſuch, that he had not been able to bring his Diſputation to any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: Which, in my Opinion, is rather a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of your Skill, than a boaſt of his own Victory. He added indeed, that if their Curioſity led them to know, how far and in what manner the Matter was carried, he could ſhew them the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and Anſwers that were written down on both ſides: Leaving them to pick out, what they could, from ſuch lame and unfiniſhed Diſcourſes. And I wonder, that you your ſelf ſhould ſuppoſe, that he aimed at the Glory of a Conqueror by thoſe Papers, ſince you cannot, but ſee, that according to the Tenor of them the Victory lies on neither Side. I ſay this on preſumption, that thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers which came to your hands, were true Copies of that which was given out by Mr. G—But becauſe it may be otherwiſe, and that a great part of your Spleen on this Occaſion may be raiſed by a miſtake, I ſhall here ſubjoin a true Copy of Mr. <hi>G—'s</hi> Paper<hi>:</hi> And that you may examine the Fidelity of it with more Convenience, a Copy likewiſe of your own (which I had from a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Gentleman of great worth and integrity) ſhall be ſet down by it in a Parallel Column, That on a due Compariſon, and maturer thoughts, you may judge, whether Mr. <hi>G—</hi> in truth deſerve ſo black a Note of inſincerity, as you are pleaſed to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98084:5"/>
lay upon him, or on the other ſide, you be obliged to make ſome amends for an ungentile and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Inſinuation.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Copy.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Dr. <hi>St—'s</hi> Copy.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 Qu. <hi>VVHether you are abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Certain that you hold now the ſame Tenets in Faith and all, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour taught to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1 <hi>Qu.</hi> VVHether you are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely certain that you hold now the ſame Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in Faith and all, that our Saviour taught to his Apoſtles?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 Anſw. <hi>We are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely certain that we now hold all the ſame Doctrin that was taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1 <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely certain that we now hold all the ſame Doctrin that was taught by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2 Qu. <hi>By what certain Rule do you hold it?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2 <hi>Qu.</hi> By what certain Rule do you hold it?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2 Anſw. <hi>By the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelations contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the writings of the New Teſtament?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2 <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelations contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the writings of the New Teſtament.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3 Qu. <hi>By what certain Rule do you know that the New Teſtament we now have, does contain all the Divine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3 <hi>Qu.</hi> By what certain Rule do you know that the New Teſtament which we now have, does contain all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3 Anſw. <hi>By the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church from the Apoſtles time downwards.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3 <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church from the Apoſtles time down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98084:5"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4 Qu. <hi>Was that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Rule to aſſure us cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly down to our time, that the New Teſtament contained all the Divine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4 <hi>Qu.</hi> Was that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Rule to aſſure us certainly down to our time, that the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament contained all the Divine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4 Anſw. <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Teſtimony of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church concerning the Book of Scripture and the Doctrin contained therein, is a ſufficient ground to make us certain of all matters that are neceſſary for our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4 <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Book of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and the Doctrin contained therein, is a ſufficient ground to make us certain of all matters that are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our Salvation.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5 Qu. <hi>Being the word</hi> Chriſtian Church <hi>may be taken in ſeveral Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes by perſons of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Religions. I deſire to know how you deſine the</hi> Chriſtian Church: <hi>Or, what it is, whoſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is ſufficient to make us abſolutely certain of all matters that are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our Salvation?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5 <hi>Qu.</hi> Being the words <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> may be taken in ſeveral Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes by perſons of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Religions, I deſire to know what that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church is whoſe Teſtimony concerning the Book of Scripture and the Doctrin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground to make us certain of all matters that are neceſſary to our Salvation?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98084:6"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5 Anſw. <hi>By the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Books of Scripture which are our Rule of Faith, as to matters of our Salvation, I mean the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Teſtimony of all Chriſtian Churches from the Apoſtles downward.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>5 <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Books of Scripture which are our Rule of Faith as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Salvation, I mean the Univerſal conſent of all Chriſtian Churches from the Apoſtles time downward.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Here Mr.</hi> T—, <hi>the Perſon for whom the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference was, being well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Doctors An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, deſired to ask Mr.</hi> G<hi>—ſome Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſaying, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Truth of his own Church, and therefore demanded how he proved theirs.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>You have here the whole and entire Writings of the firſt, longeſt and moſt Methodical Controverſie, as well according to Mr. G<hi>—s</hi> Edition as your own, wherein the difference is ſo trivial, that I dare appeal even to your own ſubtilty (who are as apt to find a Knot in a Bulruſh as another) whether or no, you have here any cauſe for complaint. And his exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98084:6"/>
in this Copy, ought to have been an Argument with you, that ſuch Errors as you found in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were rather to be attributed to the Confuſion, wherein that ſecond Diſpute ended, or ſome other Accident, than to any wilful falſification, unleſs perhaps you imagined, that the iſſue of the firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute was ſuch, as that Mr. G—could have no temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for any Forgery in the account of it, which is not greatly for your Credit, ſince this Diſpute (as I have ſaid) was that, for which the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was deſigned, and that wherein the whole time (in a manner) was taken up, it being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on as far as you were pleaſed to give it leave.</p>
            <p>At the end of that Copy of your Paper, which I received from the abovementioned Proteſtant Gentleman, I found theſe words, <hi>Here Mr.</hi> T. <hi>the perſon for whom the Conference was, being well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Doctors Anſwers, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore I have likewiſe added them in this Tranſcript, left I alſo might paſs with you for a Diſperſer of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Copies; tho', I think, the Gentleman told me, that thoſe words were only his own <hi>Memoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> of what you imparted to him by word of Mouth concerning that Diſpute: And this too I ſay, left on the other hand you ſhould arraign me for any Addition: So ſcrupulouſly careful it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves a man to be, when (for the puniſhment of his Sins) he falls into thoſe circumſtances, where not only the leaſt inadvertence is improved into a crime, but even (when nothing elſe will ſerve the turn) the cleareſt innocence is render'd guilty.</p>
            <p>And now to ſhew the World, how willing I am to do you all the right imaginable, I muſt freely
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98084:7"/>
acknowledge, that Mr. <hi>T—</hi> at the end of your laſt Anſwer in this Diſpute (as he had done a Queſtion or two before) declared, (according to what is ſet down in the abovewritten <hi>Memorandum)</hi> that he was fully ſatisfied with your Anſwers: Neither did Mr. <hi>G—</hi>ever pretend the contrary. But then, I hope, in return you will give us and others leave to judge (who give every man <hi>leave to judge</hi> in things of far greater conſequence and difficulty how far this ſatisfaction of Mr. <hi>T—</hi> was rational, and what grounds he had for it. I am ſure, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ingenious Proteſtant Gentlemen, having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed this Paper, ſaid, That Mr. <hi>T—</hi> was very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſatisfied. To conclude, your Anſwers lie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reader, and he may judge of them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>But ſince you are ſo careful that people ſhould underſtand, what was ſpoken by Mr. <hi>T—</hi> at the end of this firſt Diſpute, it is but juſt, that you ſhould give me leave to let them know, what was likewiſe ſpoken by Mr. <hi>G—</hi> tho it be not written down in theſe Copies. You may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that when Mr. <hi>G—</hi> put his Third Queſtion to you Viz. <hi>By what certain Rule do you know, that the New Teſtament which we now have; does contain all the Divine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</hi> And you Anſwered, <hi>By the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church from the Apoſtles time downward,</hi> Mr. <hi>G—</hi> preſſed you that whereas you ſaid <hi>from the Apoſtles time downward,</hi> you would declare how far downward you meant it, whether down to our times or not. You told him, That your Anſwer was already given, and that he might make the beſt of it. Now, as you ſay in your Letter, That
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98084:7"/>
Mr. <hi>G—took care in the Conference to keep you from expecting any great Ingenuity from him;</hi> ſo, if I am not miſtaken, this odd Behaviour gave him alſo a ſufficient Warning of what he was to expect from you; it being a Proceeding which look'd more like a Search after Victory or Evaſion, than Truth. But to go on: Your refuſal of ſo reaſonable a Deſire, inſtead of confounding: Mr. <hi>G—,</hi> or putting him out of the Road (as, perhaps, you thought it might have done) oblig'd him to the following Queſtion, and this Queſtion drew from you that Anſwer which you had refus'd before. Here it was that Mr. <hi>T—</hi> declar'd ſomwhat more earneſtly, how fully he was ſatisfi'd with your Anſwers, ſaying ſomwhat to this purpoſe by way of a Recapitulation, That Mr. <hi>G—</hi> had Asked, <hi>How the Proteſtants knew certainly, that they held the ſame Faith that was Taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles:</hi> It was Anſwer'd, <hi>By the Scriptures.</hi> And it being Asked, <hi>How they certainly knew they had the right Scriptures?</hi> It was Anſwer'd, <hi>By the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church.</hi> Which he look'd on as a moſt ample Satisfaction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſs'd that the Controverſie might end; and you were ſo far of his Mind, that, I remember, you urg'd it to be moſt reaſonable, that he, for whoſe ſake the Conference was deſir'd, ſhould determine when it ought to be given over. Which, indeed, had been plauſible enough, had not the progreſs that was made in the Controverſie been ſo very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and had it not been evident to you, that the Point naturally led to ſeveral Difficulties, which tho' it were not neceſſary for Mr. <hi>T—s</hi> Satisfaction (who, I ſuppoſe, brought it with him to the Conference) yet it would have become <hi>ſo great a Man at Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98084:8"/>
               <hi>as you</hi> (I do not ſay, <hi>Would be,</hi> but) <hi>are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for,</hi> to remove. For, whereas Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Third Queſtion was, <hi>By what certain Rule you knew that the New Teſtament, we now have, contain'd all the Divine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</hi> And you An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, That it was <hi>by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church.</hi> To ſay nothing of the difference in Tranſlations, as well as in the Number of the Books, it is to be explain'd how you underſtand, that <hi>all the Divine Revelations are contain'd in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> viz. Whether you mean that all neceſſary Articles of Faith are contain'd in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>virtually</hi> and <hi>implicitly,</hi> and ſo as that all, or, at leaſt, ſome of them ſtand in need of the Churches Interpretation and Authority for being made known to us, which Meaning will do you little Service; or elſe, that all ſuch Articles are contain'd in it <hi>clearly</hi> and <hi>explicitly,</hi> and ſo as that they are evident to every ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Enquirer, which is the Doctrin you commonly Teach. Now it is moſt apparent, that you are not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by the Univerſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church, that all the Divine Revelations of Chriſt and his Apoſtles are contain'd after this laſt manner in the New Teſtament, ſince all thoſe Churches in Communion with <hi>Rome,</hi> and divers others, poſitively affirm the contrary; So that if the Abſolute Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Entireneſs of your Faith have no other Ground, than a pretended Univerſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church, that all neceſſary Articles are <hi>plainly</hi> and <hi>explicitly</hi> contain'd in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that in reality there be no ſuch Univerſal Teſtimony (as it is undeniable there is none) it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follows, that your <hi>Abſolute Certainty</hi> is wholly groundleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98084:8"/>
You ſee, Sir, how main a Point ought to have been ſpoken to, before you and Mr. G—had taken your leaves of this Subject.</p>
            <p>But Mr. G—waving this neceſſary Branch of the Controverſie for that preſent, was willing to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand firſt, what you meant by your <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony,</hi> and how far it extended. He therefore preſs'd you to know, what you meant by the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church,</hi> on whoſe Teſtimony you rely'd. Here Mr. <hi>T—</hi> once more profeſs'd his Satisfaction, and you again thought he had ſo much cauſe for it, that you were very loth the Diſputation ſhould proceed any farther. But being told, That ſeeing we were to receive the Rule of our Faith from the Teſtimony of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> it was but reaſonable that we ſhould know what that <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> was, to which we ought to have recourſe, eſpecially ſince there were ſo many different Opinions concerning it, you were at length content that Mr. <hi>G—</hi> ſhould ſet down his Fifth Queſtion, which was thus<hi>—Being the Words</hi> Chriſtian Church <hi>may be taken in divers Latitudes by Perſons of different Religions, I deſire to know, what that</hi> Chriſtian Church <hi>is, whoſe Teſtimony concerning the Book of Scripture, and the Doctrin contain'd therein, is a ſufficient Ground to make us certain of all Matters, that are neceſſary to our Salvation.</hi> I put in the Words of your own Copy. Here we expected (as, I ſuppoſe, all my Readers would have done) that you would have given us a Definition, or Deſcription of the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> But inſtead of this you tell us, That <hi>by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Teſtimony of the Chriſtian Church,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>you mean the Conſent of all Chriſtian Churches from the Apoſtles Time downward.</hi> Was not this Trifling?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98084:9"/>
Who doubts, but that the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, muſt conſiſt of all Chriſtian Churches in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular? Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Intention was (as you might eaſily ſee) to know what Churches in this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you accounted <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> (i.e.) Parts of the Univerſal <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church: Whether you took in all thoſe Congregations, who made any Profeſſion of Believing in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or requir'd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more (and what it was you requir'd) for the Qualifying them for particular Chriſtian Churches, or Parts of the Univerſal Chriſtian Church. And therefore expreſly he asked you, Whether you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the <hi>Arians, Neſtorians, Eutychians,</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts,</hi> and urg'd that this Queſtion might likewiſe be written down. You reply'd, That <hi>it ſhould not be written, unleſs it were by Conſent;</hi> And you did not conſent, becauſe Mr. <hi>T—</hi>declar'd (now more loudly than before) that he was fully ſatisfi'd, and deſir'd to propoſe a new Queſtion to Mr. <hi>G—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Mr. <hi>G—</hi> was forc'd to break off, and thus ended that Point, which was deſign'd for the whole Subject of the Conference; but whether with much Glory to you, or much Shame to Mr. <hi>G—,</hi> I leave the moſt partial of my Readers to judge. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when you had given leave for Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Fifth Queſtion, you ought to have permitted his Sixth, ſince it tended only to obtain that Anſwer, which you could not but perceive was aim'd at by his Fifth, viz. <hi>What Churches you look'd on as Members of the Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have here laid before you, the moſt material Paſſages and Circumſtances of this Firſt Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſincerely (I call God to Witneſs) as I have been able, and as ſuccinctly (according to my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98084:9"/>
Judgment) as the Nature of the Thing would bear, and could agree with that fulneſs in the Account, which I promiſed at firſt. I have, indeed, been ſomewhat the more Particular in it, in regard that you ſay little, or nothing thereof, whereas one would have expected, that whilſt you pretend to give a <hi>True Account</hi> of this Conference, you would not have paſs'd by in ſilence ſo conſiderable a Part of it, not to ſay, in a manner the Whole. I am ſure, that if you have any reaſon to complain, that Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Copies were imperfect, he hath much more to ſay, that your <hi>True Account</hi> is ſo: For if in his Paper there be a Twig miſſing in one of the Branches, the very Trunk or Body of the Tree is wanting in your Account; So eaſie it is to imagine Faults in others, and ſo hard to ſee them in our ſelves! And ſo true, that the Mote is more diſcernible to us in our Brothers Eye, than the BEAM in our own.</p>
            <p>Having finiſh'd what I had to ſay concerning this Firſt and Chief Controverſie, I ſhall uſe the ſame Sincerity in giving you both Copies of the Second; in which, as it happen'd when the Spirits of the Diſputants grew warmer, ſo (eſpecially towards the Concluſion, as I have ſaid above) the Noiſe and Wrangling might hinder the Writers from being ſo exact. However even here, the Difference is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, that an ordinary Charity would rather lay the blame of it on a caſual Error, than any wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miſtake.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98084:10"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Copy.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Dr. <hi>St—'s</hi> Copy.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Qu. <hi>HOw do you prove the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1 <hi>Qu.</hi> HOw do you prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be Infallible?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Anſ. <hi>By the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>I mean all the Churches in Communion with</hi> Rome; <hi>and this Church I hold to be Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, by following the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Teſtimony of all Traditionary Chriſtians (that is to ſay) by holding the ſame Doctrin to Day that was delivered Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, in Faith, and ſo up to the Time of our Bleſſed Saviour: For if they follow this Rule they can never Err in Faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are Infallible.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1 <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I mean all the Churches in Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>Rome;</hi> and this Church I hold to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, by following, the Univerſal Teſtimony of all Traditionary Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that is to ſay, by holding the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin to day that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered yeſterday (in Faith) and ſo up to the time of our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for if they follow this Rule, they can never err in Faith, and therefore are Infallible.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Qu. <hi>How do's it appear that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is Infallible in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2 <hi>Qu.</hi> How do's it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is Infallible in the ſenſe and meaning of Tradition, and is this Tradition a Rule of Faith diſtinct from Scripture or no?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Anſ. <hi>All Traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Chriſtians, that is, all Biſhops, all Prieſts, all Fathers, and all People following this Rule, and receiving Faith, becauſe it was received the Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, could not Innovate in Faith, unleſs they could all, either forget what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the day before, or out of Malice change it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe no cauſe can be aſſigned for ſuch an effect, they cannot Innovate: If there can? Aſſign it.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2 <hi>Anſw.</hi> All Traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
Chriſtians, that is, all Biſhops, all Prieſts, all Fathers, and all People following this Rule, and receiving Faith, becauſe it was received the day before, could not inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate in Faith, unleſs they could all either forget what they received the day before, or out of Malice change it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe no cauſe can be aſſigned for ſuch an effect, they cannot innovate: If they can? Aſſign it.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98084:10"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3 Qu. <hi>Whether the Greek Church did follow from Father to Son the Tradition in matters of Faith, or no?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3 <hi>Qu.</hi> Did not the Greek Church follow Tradition from Father to Son, and yet err in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, ſo that a Church pretending to follow Tradition may err in matters of Faith?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3 Anſw. <hi>Till they left that Rule and took up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo fell into Error as the</hi> Calviniſts <hi>did.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3 <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Greek Church followed Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion till the <hi>Arians</hi> left that Rule, and took up a new one, that is, Scripture privately interpreted.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Dr. <hi>St—</hi> I ſpeak not of the <hi>Arians</hi> but of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Greek Church.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98084:11"/>
The chief defect, which you here ſeem to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of in Mr. <hi>G—s</hi> Paper, is in the Third Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> That it being ſet down, <hi>Whether the Greek Church did follow Tradition from Father to Son, or no?</hi> The inference which you drew from it, is left out. Now it is ſo palpably evident to any one, who reads the preceding Queſtions and Anſwers, for what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you asked that Queſtion, and conſequently, <hi>What inference you drew from it,</hi> that it cannot be imagined, Mr. <hi>G's</hi> Amanuenſis ſhould have any deſign in leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out thoſe words, unleſs it were to ſpare unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary pains; it being manifeſt, that you produced the example of the Greek Church, to diſprove what had been ſaid before, touching the Infallibility of Tradition<hi>:</hi> So that, in my Opinion, this ought not to have been the occaſion of any miſunderſtanding between you.</p>
            <p>But whereas you ſay, that Mr. <hi>G—</hi> grants you in his Anſwer, that <hi>the Greek Church followed Tradition:</hi> If you mean, that <hi>they followed it, even when they fell into error.</hi> I find no ſuch thing in his Anſwer, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to his Copy nor yours. But if you mean, That <hi>the Greek Church followed Tradition, till they erred.</hi> This is no plainer in your Copy, than it is in his.</p>
            <p>To your Inſtance of the Greek Church, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Mr. <hi>G—</hi> anſwered, That <hi>they adhered to Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on till the time of the Arians,</hi> but whether or no, he dictated his Anſwer in thoſe terms, when it came to be written down, I have forgotten. Neither do I remember, that your laſt ſaying, (viz.) <hi>I mean not the Arians, &amp;c.</hi> which is left out in Mr. <hi>G's</hi> Copy, was written down. I believe, that neither Mr. <hi>T—</hi>nor the Gentleman, who wrote for Mr. <hi>G—</hi>had it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98084:11"/>
in their Copies: Neither do I think that your own Amanuenſis wrote it whilſt Mr. <hi>G—</hi>ſtayed. At leaſt, I am confident that it was not <hi>ſet down by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and therefore not according to that Law, which you had obſerved in the former Diſputation: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I muſt ingenuouſly confeſs (as I have done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready) that this Point was not fully cleared<hi>:</hi> For (before your Reply, <hi>viz. that you meant not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, &amp;c.</hi> was written down, which, according to the Method of this Conference, had been Mr. <hi>G's</hi> time of Anſwering) ſome mutual Reproaches (which were begun by your ſelf) ariſing between you and your Adverſary, Mr. <hi>T—</hi>roſe up (as I have ſaid) and deſired, there might be no farther words in this matter, foraſmuch as he was fully ſatisfied, ſaying (as he himſelf hath ſince reminded me) that <hi>ſeeing the Greek Church, which</hi> (as it ſeems he fancied) <hi>was <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal, had erred, it was evident to him, that an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church might err,</hi> with ſomewhat more to the like purpoſe, and of the like ſtrain. I ſay, theſe heats of our Diſputants, and this importunity of Mr. <hi>T—,</hi> were the true Cauſes of our parting in ſo great a hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, inſomuch that all thoſe things which were ſpoken were not written, nor ſome (perhaps) of what was written ſo nicely exact, as not to leave room for the cavils of one, who might be more concerned for the peculiar credit of Learning in himſelf, than for the ordinary reputation of Integrity in his Adverſary.</p>
            <p>You ſay, That Mr. <hi>G—roſe up, and endeavoured to hinder the Writers from ſetting down this latter part, as it ought to have been:</hi> And herein you ſeem to own what I have ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> That in the latter part of this Diſpute things were not ſet down ſo exactly as they ought to have been. And, conſequently, what you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98084:12"/>
ſay of an <hi>Original Paper read aloud and approved by both Parties,</hi> muſt not be underſtood of a Paper containing the whole Conference; for, how came it to paſs, that in a Paper approved by both Parties, all things were not ſet down, as they ought to have been? But whereas you ſay that Mr. <hi>G—</hi>endeavoured to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſetting down of theſe things, I dare ſay, that if you examin your Conſcience once more, you will find no ſuch thought in it: For my own part, I am confident, that if you had deſired Mr. <hi>G—</hi> (which you did not) to have ſtayed, for the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and comparing theſe laſt words, he would moſt readily have complied with you, which is more than you would do with him (as I have ſhewed) in your former Diſputation, in which you were as much beholding to Mr. <hi>T—</hi> for his deſire of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the Diſcourſe, as you can fancy that Mr. <hi>G—</hi>was obliged to him for a like importunity in this. Mr. <hi>T</hi>'s importunity was the ſame in both occaſions, but in the former Mr. <hi>G—</hi> deſired that his Queſtion might be written down, and was not heard, whereas in the latter you asked no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>But, beſides what I have already ſaid, it might have been expected, that you, who have been ſo much verſed in theſe Polemic Diſcourſes, and are ſo well skill'd in all the Laws relating to them, when you ſaw two ſeveral Copies of this Conference car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of your Houſe, would have taken care that they might have been compared, or, at leaſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it, eſpecially when (as you ſay) Mr. <hi>G—</hi> had <hi>taken care</hi> in the Conference to keep you from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting any great ingenuity from him after it. If you will take my judgment on the Caſe (which, I think, is not very raſh) you hoped for greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98084:12"/>
from this Omiſſion (which was as much your fault, as Mr. G<hi>'s)</hi> by having ſome appearance of an Objection, than you could have received from the Conference, had it been publiſhed to the World, even in your own Copy.</p>
            <p>You ſay, you <hi>know, what Arts have been uſed to get Mr.</hi> T<hi>—to approve Mr.</hi> G—s <hi>Copy.</hi> And I believe, that neither Mr. <hi>G—,</hi> nor any of his Friends, nor even Mr. <hi>T—</hi> himſelf knows any ſuch. At leaſt, Mr. <hi>T—</hi> told me not long ſince, that he himſelf was diſſatisfied with this expreſſion of yours. But leſt the World ſhould think that your Inſinuation is wholly without pretence (and that, at the ſame time, it may know, how great an Improver one may be) I will acknowledge, that once meeting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally with Mr. <hi>T—</hi> in the Street, I told him, <hi>I heard, you complained that Mr.</hi> G—s <hi>Papers of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference were falſe, and therefore I deſired him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his Copy with that which was written for Mr.</hi> G—, <hi>That we might ſee, whether Mr.</hi> G<hi>—or his</hi> Amanuenſis <hi>had dealt fairly, or not.</hi> Which was all I ſaid, and (as I underſtand by Mr. <hi>T—)</hi> all the ground you have for this Aſperſion. What could be more natural, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent or juſt than this proceeding? But Dr. <hi>St—</hi>knows <hi>what Arts were uſed.</hi> Would to God, that neither he nor I had any worſe. But I believe, that this very Inſinuation will appear at the laſt Day to be a worſe Art, than any were uſed on this occaſion with Mr. <hi>T—.</hi> If Mr. <hi>T—</hi> had informed you of any Bribes, Promiſes, Threats or any kind of Perſwaſions, that had been made uſe of, for the corrupting him to the Approbation of our Copy, you would have done well to have laid them open; but if a bare deſire that Mr. <hi>T—</hi> would compare his Copy with ours,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98084:13"/>
muſt paſs for a deſign of corrupting him; I think, it would be convenient, that for the future we pull not off our Hats to this Mr. <hi>T—</hi>when we meet him, leſt it ſhould be interpreted, that we ſtill court him to our Party. But, I preſume, I need not take much pains, to wipe off this Aſperſion, ſince I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but perſwade my ſelf, that my Readers, when they have peruſed the abovewritten Copies, will conclude with me that Mr. <hi>G—</hi>had no great occaſion for theſe Arts, and that the offering a Temptation of that nature to ſo zealous a Proteſtant as Mr. <hi>T—,</hi> muſt do his cauſe more harm, than he could receive bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by his yielding to it.</p>
            <p>To conclude: I pray, Sir, what worſe Art was it, for us to deſire Mr. <hi>T—</hi>to compare his Copy with ours, than it was for you, to deſire the Gentleman who wrote for Mr. <hi>G.</hi> to compare his with yours? But Eating, Drinking, Sleeping are natural Actions in Dr. <hi>St—</hi>and at the ſame time, Arts and Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in Mr. <hi>G—.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, that when you had deſired Mr. <hi>T—</hi>to bring that Gentleman to you, word was left with your Servant, that <hi>he was not well.</hi> I know not what Myſtery you likewiſe make of this. But I aſſure you, That, when this hapned, the Gentleman you mention, told me, <hi>you had ſent for him, but that he had entred on a Courſe of Phyſick, and could not conveniently wait on you till that were over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay further, that <hi>ſuppoſing he</hi> (Mr. <hi>G—</hi>or his Amanuenſis) <hi>ſhould correct his Copy, this will be too late for your Vindication, ſince ſo many imperfect ones have been given out and diſperſed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and therefore you are forced to take this way</hi> (i. e. publiſh this Letter) <hi>to put a ſtop to ſuch diſingenuous proceeding.</hi> This, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98084:13"/>
is what I cannot comprehend. You complain, that you have ſuffered by falſe Copies: And will it not be a ſufficient reparation, to have theſe falſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies recalled, or diſown'd, and true ones publiſhed in their ſtead? And here let me tell you, that it is not a little wondred at, why you your ſelf had not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a True Copy of this Conference, (eſpecially ſince you tell us of an Original approved by both Parties) which would have been a more natural and proper way of putting a ſtop to the <hi>diſingenuous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding,</hi> you ſpeak of, than that which you have tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en. Certainly, there can be no cauſe aſſigned for this Omiſſion, unleſs it be, that, in truth, you are as little pleaſed with the true Copies, as the falſe ones, which may ſerve for a new Argument, that the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between them is not very great, and alſo for another Inference, which the Reader will make.</p>
            <p>Beſides, had you, aſſoon as theſe imperfect Copies came to your hands, ſent to Mr. <hi>G—</hi> to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no they were given out by him, and in caſe they were, had you ſhewn him the Errors of them, and deſired their amendment, none could have blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you: But ſo long after, to take the opportunity of his abſence, and, to accuſe him in this public manner without firſt hearing what he had to ſay, either, in the full defence of himſelf, or, at leaſt, in the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of his faults, was in my Opinion neither an <hi>ingenuous</hi> nor Chriſtian proceeding.</p>
            <p>You tell us after this, <hi>you hear that I</hi> (for ſo, I am told, you underſtand by Mr. <hi>M—) pretend you gave out falſe Copies.</hi> But what I pretended, was (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what you will have read before) that I had ſeen a Copy which was ſaid to be taken from yours, that in the principal Controverſie it differed nothing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98084:14"/>
from Mr. <hi>G's,</hi> and that in the other, the difference was not ſo conſiderable, but it might well ariſe from the confuſion or abruptneſs wherein the Diſputation ended; that foraſmuch as concerned your laſt Clauſe, <hi>viz. I mean not the Arians, &amp;c.</hi> I verily believed that it was not written down whilſt we ſtayed, at leaſt, not ſo as to be taken notice of by both Parties, or by conſent, which you looked on as a neceſſary circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for the ſetting down of former Points. Now if any one interpreted this, <hi>a Pretending that you gave out a falſe Copy,</hi> it is more than I could prevent: For my own part, I never termed it ſo, being loth to lay the ſevereſt Cenſure on things for which there may be ſome color; and therefore tho'I was perſwaded that this <hi>Diſputed Clauſe</hi> was not ſet down according to our Rule, <hi>viz. by Conſent,</hi> I could never prevail with my ſelf to accuſe your Copy of downright falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe I remembred that you ſaid thoſe words, and that Mr. <hi>G—</hi> (as far as I can call to mind) return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no expreſs Anſwer, being diverted from it, as I have already ſhewn. However had Mr. <hi>G—</hi> taken the ſame liberty, and after his departure written down, that Queſtion which he asked you at the end of the firſt Diſputation, I am afraid you would not have been ſo civil or ſcrupulous, as not to have called his Copy falſe. For how could this be expected, when you now take a far leſs occaſion (if it may be ſtiled an occaſion) for ſo great a Defamation?</p>
            <p>You tell Mr. <hi>G—,</hi> that <hi>becauſe his Writer's Copy was not read, and none ſigned, you deſire him to make good two things, which,</hi> you ſay, <hi>the whole Conference depended on.</hi> Now, I ſhould have thought, that <hi>becauſe Mr.</hi> G's <hi>Copy was not read, and none ſigned,</hi> you would have deſired, that both Copies might have been read, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98084:14"/>
on, and Sign'd, and ſo Diſperſed, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Damage accru'd to either Side from the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of former Copies, might be repair'd and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by theſe perfect ones, for the future. But inſtead of this to tell us, that becauſe the Papers were not Read and Signed, you expect that a new Diſpute ſhould be commenc'd, what is it but to confirm what I have already intimated, <hi>viz.</hi> that you are not much in love with either Copy, and the Conference it ſelf is as little to your Satisfaction, as the worſt Account of it?</p>
            <p>I know not what Mr. <hi>G—</hi> will return to your Challenge, but I muſt confeſs, I do not ſee with what reaſon you can term it <hi>a juſt and neceſſary Vindication of your ſelf.</hi> For, if you are deſirous that the World ſhould have a true Account of what paſs'd in the Conference, the abovemention'd Papers compar'd and adjuſted, will effect this much better than a new Diſpute: For, tho' you ſhould overcome in it, will it therefore follow that you had the better in the Conference? And again, tho' Mr. <hi>G—</hi> ſhould carry away the Palm in this Second Engagement, will it thence appear how Innocent or Guilty he was in the publication of his Paper? You ſee, Sir, how impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ineffectual a Way you propoſe either for your Juſtification, or Mr. <hi>G's:</hi> and how convenient it is for both, that the Writings of the Conference ſhould be adjuſted and publiſh'd (if you are not contented with thoſe which you find here) ſince it is not Skill, or the Merits of the Firſt Cauſe, but the Sincerity of the Perſons which is now in Queſtion.</p>
            <p>But if you judge, that the Diſputations of the Conference are lame and imperfect, I am of your Mind. And therefore, if you think fit to propoſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98084:15"/>
that, in order to the drawing things to a Concluſion, both Parties may be oblig'd to go on where they left off: I dare promiſe you, that Mr. G—will give you a fair Meeting at any ſuch reaſonable Time or Place, as you ſhall appoint. And leſt you ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of ſuffering any more by falſe Copies, I queſtion not but you will have his Conſent, to have them taken by ſworn Notaries, or even by your own <hi>Amanuenſis,</hi> and (for greater Security) in the preſence of as many and as credible Witneſſes as you pleaſe. And here you have as <hi>fair an Opportunity of ſhewing your ſelf</hi> as you offer Mr. G—; Only, I ſuppoſe, he will ask one Favor of you, which is, That ſuch an Umpire may be choſen, as will give a free ſcope to the Diſcourſe, and not cut it off, before any thing be concluded, as Mr. <hi>T.</hi> dealt by this.</p>
            <p>I ſay not theſe things out of any apprehenſion I have, that Mr. G—would find much difficulty, in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking that Province which you are pleas'd to put upon him, ſo far, at leaſt, as it concerns his former Arguments; but becauſe I judge this a moſt imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Method in our preſent Difference, as, I doubt not, but it will appear to any one, whoſe Partiality has not robb'd him of his common Senſe.</p>
            <p>But, beſides what I have alledged above in this Matter, it is my Opinion, that Truth is not ſo eaſily diſcover'd to ſuch as are miſtaken, by large Books of Controverſie, as by theſe Conferences, eſpecially when they are faithfully Penn'd down, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the general View. And this for the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Few Men have Leiſure, or (at leaſt) Induſtry enough for the peruſal of large Treatiſes; whereas one of theſe Conferences ſeldom reaches to above a Sheet of Paper.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98084:15"/>
2. Men are commonly ſo well perſwaded of the Truth of their own Party, or elſe ſo willing to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of it, that for the moſt part they only Read their own Authors, and ſo become, at beſt, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judges, eſpecially when they happen to be on that Side which ſtands in need of ſome inſincere Dealing for its ſupport. Whereas in theſe Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, the Arguments on both Sides being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably ſet down, and mixt with one another, it will not be poſſible for the Reader to read and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the one, without reading and conſidering the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſtrength of the Arguments is more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, when they are thus plac'd by one another, according to the Maxim, <hi>Contraria juxtà ſe poſita ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eluceſcunt:</hi> As it is alſo, when they are laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us naked, and ſtript of all thoſe artificial Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Rhetorick and Satyr, which make up a great part of our late Controverſial Volumes, and ſerve for nothing elſe, than to amuſe and deceive an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary and unskilful Reader, who is inclin'd to think, that he, who ſays moſt, hath moſt to ſay, and that he, who hath the beſt Jeſt, hath likewiſe the beſt Argument.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In theſe Conferences the Diſputants have not ſo great an opportunity of wreſting and perverting one anothers Arguments, as they have, when each Party ſitting in his Study, and (as it were) on his own Dunghil, hath his Adverſary at his Mercy, and makes him ſpeak what he hath a mind to, by diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and miſrepreſenting his Arguments, or elſe changeth the State of the Queſtion, and impoſeth a new Task upon him, dealing with him as Conjurers are ſaid to do with the Devil, who, when they have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98084:16"/>
rais'd him, are taught never to let him reſt, but as ſoon as one Buſineſs is diſpatch'd, or even before 'tis quite done, to employ him in another, leſt otherwiſe he might want Work, and then deſtroy the Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to keep himſelf from Idleneſs.</p>
            <p>And we have not far to go for ſome Inſtance of this nature: For you are pleas'd to ſay, that the Conference whereof we now ſpeak, depended on two things to be prov'd by Mr. <hi>G—</hi> (1.) That you <hi>[Proteſtants]</hi> have no <hi>abſolute Certainty,</hi> as to the Rule of your Faith, viz. <hi>The Scripture,</hi> altho' you have a larger and firmer <hi>Tradition</hi> for it, viz. <hi>The Conſent of all Chriſtian Churches,</hi> than we <hi>[Catholics]</hi> can have for the Points of Faith in difference between us. (2.) That the Tradition from Father to Son is an infallible Conveyance of Matters of Faith, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Greek Church</hi> is charg'd by us <hi>[Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics]</hi> with Error, which adher'd to Tradition.</p>
            <p>Now, as to the Firſt, it is not deny'd, That there is, in truth, an <hi>abſolute Certainty</hi> for that Scripture wherein you agree with us; but that according to your Principles (who at the time of your Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion charg'd all Chriſtian Churches with Errors, not only in other Articles of their Belief, but even in the Tradition or Delivery of Scripture, and yet rely on the Tradition of theſe Churches for it) any ſuch Certainty can be ſhewn.</p>
            <p>We ſay farther, that, whereas you pretend to an abſolute Certainty as to the Rule of your Faith from the Conſent of all Chriſtian Churches; you ſeem to forget, that your Rule is Scripture, not as Interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (or to be Interpreted) by the Church, but as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood (or to be underſtood without a neceſſity of ſubmitting to the Interpretation of the Church) by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98084:16"/>
every ſober Enquirer, tho' of the meaneſt capacity, for which Rule (as you know well enough) you are very far from having the Conſent of all Chriſtian Churches. To which purpoſe I ſpoke before.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we deſire to know (according to what I have likewiſe ſaid above) what thoſe <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> are, whoſe Teſtimony is required towards the aſſuring us, what is Scripture and what not, and by what mark you diſtinguiſh them from others: Since we cannot ſuppoſe, that in this Caſe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Concurrence of all Heretical Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which may profeſs a Belief in Chriſt, and call themſelves Chriſtians, foraſmuch as theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them (ſome denying one Book of Scripture and ſome another) either have, or may deny the whole Canon. And for this reaſon, you ought to ſhew us by what Rule we are able to diſcern the Orthodox Deliverers of Scripture from the Heterodox, leſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we may be deceived by receiving too little or too much for Canonical. And this was that Task, which remained on your hands, when the firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation broke off. But here inſtead of finiſhing it, you finely diſguiſe it, and by a certain Controverſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juggle put it into the hands of your Adverſary, as tho' it belonged to him.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Point, you would make the World believe, that it lay on Mr. <hi>G—</hi>to prove, that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>The Greek Church erred, whilſt it adhered to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> a Church adhering to Tradition could not err: Whereas Mr. <hi>G—</hi> never acknowledged, that <hi>the Greek Church erred, whilſt it adhered to Tradition;</hi> and therefore to ſuppoſe it, as you do, was to beg the Queſtion, and miſrepreſent the State of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98084:17"/>
Wherefore, to ſtay no longer on this Subject, I beg of my Readers to weigh your two Propoſitions, and compare them carefully with the two Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to which they belong; and if after that, they ſhall conclude, that each Queſtion is rightly Stated by you, and that the Proof in both is incumbent on Mr. G—, as you would have it, I will be contented that my Fourth Reaſon againſt Diſputing by Books, <hi>(viz.</hi> the hazard of Miſrepreſentation) ſhall go for nothing.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Much time is ſpent by Controverſie-Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, not only in proving certain Propoſitions which would be granted them by their Adverſaries, but alſo in raiſing ſilly Objections, which their Adverſaries neither have, nor are like to make. Which two things (beſides the loſs of Time, which is no ſmall miſchief) are very apt to miſguide one, who is not reſolved to hear both ſides, by making him think, that what his Author is ſo ſolicitous to prove, muſt neceſſarily be denied by the adverſe Party, and that what the one labors to refute, the other muſt have Objected, or, at leaſt, be likely to Object. And what an erroneous Idea muſt ſuch a perſon have of his Authors Adverſaries, whilſt he takes thoſe weak Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations and Denials to be Theirs, which are not ſo in effect?</p>
            <p>Now, theſe Inconveniences are avoided by a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Conference, where nothing is proved but what is denied, and nothing refuted but what is really Objected. Hereby the loſs of time is prevented, the juſt reputation of the Diſputants and the due me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of each Cauſe preſerved, and (what is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable) a great hindrance to the diſcovery of Truth removed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98084:17"/>
Sixthly, The multiplication of large Volumes of Controverſie is apt to breed a conceit in very many, that an Enquiry after Truth is both difficult and fruitleſs: And therefore they often chuſe, rather to deſpair with eaſe, than to labour (as they fancy) without any hope of Succeſs. Whereas theſe ſhorter Conferences will either ſatisfie them ſooner, or, at leaſt, more eaſily engage them in ſo neceſſary a ſearch.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral other Reaſons which might be alledged to the ſame purpoſe, but I think, theſe are ſufficient to convince the World, that if Mr. G—ſhould prefer a perſonal Conference to the Writing of Books (as, I hope, he will) it would not be any Tergiverſation, but the choice of the beſt and moſt uſeful way of deciding Controverſies, and particularly this. And ſince you are now become the Challenger, he ought (according to the Laws of Duel) to chuſe his Weapon, or manner of Fight.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have found fault with you, and now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, it will not be amiſs, if I acknowledge an Error or Weakneſs of my own, which is, that at firſt I imagin ed my ſelf to have found a great advantage againſt you, by a Reflection, which I (and ſeveral others) made on the peruſal of your two Propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> That in your firſt you ſeem to affirm, that the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all Chriſtian Churches, which (ſpeaking in general) you call in your Diſputation the Chriſtian Church, is a ground of <hi>Abſolute Certainty</hi> for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance of Scripture: And in your Second you would infer, That Tradition is no <hi>infallible Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> of Matters of Faith. Now ſuppoſing it a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Faith, that all the Books of Scripture owned by you, were inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, (that is,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98084:18"/>
               <hi>are true Scripture)</hi> as, I preſume, you will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I do not ſee, but your Propoſitions contradict one another, and we have once more Dr. <hi>St.</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>St. viz.</hi> Tradition the ground of <hi>Abſolute Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>no infallible Conveyance</hi> on the other. I muſt confeſs (I ſay) that I looked on this Implication, as manifeſt to that degree, that it would not be eaſie for you to get clear of it; but when I conſidered, how great a Talent you have, of reconciling (what we ordinary Folks account) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, and how evident you have already made it, That a Church may be <hi>true,</hi> and yet <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> and that Roman Catholics may be <hi>ſaved,</hi> and yet by being Roman Catholics muſt be <hi>guilty of Sins inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with Salvation,</hi> I thought it more adviſable to let this new <hi>ſeeming Contradiction</hi> paſs Muſter, than to offer an occaſion for more Volumes of that kind. However you muſt give me leave to tell you, that when you have ſufficiently proved the firſt of theſe Propoſitions, which (if any Body's) is truly your Task, <hi>viz. That Tradition is a ground of abſolute Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty for the receiving of the Scripture:</hi> It is ten to one, but you furniſh Mr. <hi>G—</hi>with Arguments to prove the Second, which is his Province, <hi>viz. That Tradition is an Infallible Conveyance of Matters of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope, my Readers will not imagin by what they find here, that I have any purpoſe of being engaged in theſe Diſputations. It would be too great an Arrogance for me to pretend, either to ſucceed Mr. <hi>G—,</hi> or to oppoſe Dr. <hi>St—.</hi> And therefore I have medled with the Controverſie no farther, than I thought it neceſſary to the clearing of Matter of Fact, by ſhewing (as well as I could) how the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98084:18"/>
were carried on, how they ended, what ſtill remained to be proved by both Sides, and to what manner of Proving <hi>(viz.</hi> Whether by Perſonal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, or otherwiſe) they ſeemed to be obliged. In a word, my Deſign hath been nothing elſe, than (as far as I have been able) to reſcue Mr. G—from thoſe Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which your Accuſation and Challenge would bring upon him, till ſuch time as he himſelf may have an opportunity of doing it more fully by his own Pen. But I ſuppoſe, enough is ſhewed already, to convince the World, that if in the Conference the Victory lay on your ſide, you were not much miſtaken, when you thought it <hi>not worth boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſeem (to many of your Readers) to lay ſome ſtreſs on Mr. <hi>G's going</hi> to Coffee-Houſes, and your <hi>not going</hi> to them, as if therefore the more Credit were to be given to you, and the leſs to him. But, I do not think, that you could have any ſuch meaning, when I find, you had your main Intelligence concerning Mr. <hi>G's</hi> behaviour, from thoſe Houſes, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by ſuch perſons as made no ſcruple of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting them, whom, I preſume, you would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſo eaſily and thoroughly as you do, did you eſteem them the leſs credible for thoſe viſits. I know, many Lies are told in Coffee-houſes; but if all places were to be avoided, wherein Lies are told, I am afraid, that Dr. <hi>St—</hi>would run the hazard of being ſilenced for want of a Pulpit, which might be ventur'd on.</p>
            <p>Certainly, it is no Crime to go to Coffee-houſes: tho', I confeſs, to talk in them as many do, is a very great one. But inſtead of this, if any one ſhould (as far as Prudence and Opportunity will give way)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98084:19"/>
divert thoſe Diſcourſes from what is Seditious, Idle or Profane, to that which is ſerious, and uſeful, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for this life or the next, he would be ſo far from committing a fault, that he would prevent many; and, perhaps, by leaving ſome good impreſſion or other in thoſe he converſes with, do a greater Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Common-wealth, and to Almighty God; than if he had kept at home. But this is a kind of Miſſionary Zeal, and therefore what the Children of the Reformation are little acquainted with.</p>
            <p>However, foraſmuch as concerns the Coffee-Houſes, we have far more in them of Dr. <hi>St's</hi> Coat, than of Mr. <hi>G's.</hi> But whether with any better mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive than that of entertaining and recreating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I will not determine. And therefore if it paſs for looſneſs, or want of due Gravity, to viſit a Coffee-houſe, I deſire Dr. <hi>St—</hi>to tell me, what Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit leads ſo many of his own Brethren thither. But ſome people, ſo they may ſtrike thoſe, whom they take for their Enemies, care not, if at the ſame time, they fall foul on their Friends.</p>
            <p>But for ſuch as cry ſo often <hi>What have we to do with Religion in a Coffee-houſe?</hi> I would fain know of them; whether or no, it be lawful to viſit any Place or Converſation, where it will be improper to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, or Edifie our Neighbor? For my part, I think, it is not. And therefore if a Coffee-houſe be a place, wherein Religion is not to be medled with, I ſhall be of Dr. <hi>St's</hi> mind (if his mind be ſuch) and conclude, That it ought not to be viſited.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I remember, that during the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference you complain'd of want of Time (which, as I ſhould have told you, was alſo a principal occaſion of Mr. <hi>T's</hi> haſt) it will not be fit that I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98084:19"/>
ſhould detain you much longer: And therefore to the mean Opinion which you ſeem to expreſs of your Adverſary, I ſhall only ſay, that, methinks, you ought not to make us think ſo poorly of our ſelves, whilſt you endeavour to perſwade us, that we have no need of any Guide in the moſt My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Things, ſince nothing can be a greater Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for the neceſſity of Direction, than the ſight of our own Weakneſs. Wherefore, if you pleaſe, let us compound the Buſineſs. We will be contented to paſs for Weak and Ignorant, and you ſhall be obliged to ſhew, by whom we may be protected from Error: It being moſt uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be ſhewn, that we ought not to truſt our Reaſon, and to be told that we ought. And I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but you will effectually perform this, whenever you comply with what appears to be your Task already, and give us ſome diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mark, for the finding out thoſe Chriſtians, on whoſe Tradition we may ſafely rely for the reception of the Holy Scriptures; ſince (if we may venture on <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Aug. libro contra Epiſt. Fundamenti.</hi> Ego verò E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelio non crederem, niſi me Catholicae Eccleſiae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveret Authoritas. Quibus ergo obtemperavi dicentibus, <hi>Credite Evangelio,</hi> cur eis non obtemperem dicentibus mihi, <hi>Noli credere Manichaeo,</hi> &amp;c.</note> St. <hi>Auguſtins</hi> Judgment) it would be a Madneſs to disbelieve thoſe in any other Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Faith, whom we believe in ſo important a Point. Tell us then, from whom we are to receive the Scriptures; and we will not ask you, to whom we ought to go for Certainty in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctrins.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98084:20"/>
I have but one thing more to acquaint you with, which is, that tho' I have ſhewn that the Anſwering your Challenge hath nothing to do with our preſent Diſpute, and that even for the finiſhing of the firſt Controverſies, I like Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, better than Writing; yet there are ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us who think, that you ought not to want your ſatisfaction, even in that way, which you will ſuppoſe the <hi>leaſt liable to the injury of falſe Copies.</hi> And conſequently your Objection concerning the Greek Church is undertaken, which being the Argument you ſeem fondeſt of, and that which you have pickt out of the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to flouriſh with in your Letter, I promiſe my ſelf that my News will be very grateful to you, and here in the Cloſe make ſome kind of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, for any Term or Expreſſion, which (through my attending oftentimes more to the nature of the Things treated of, than to the Dignity of the Perſon with whom I treat) may have ſlipt from my Pen, leſs agreeing with that Reſpect, wherewith I deſire to continue,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant E. M.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>March 28. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98084:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98084:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
